VINÍCIUS BORGES

Data Analyst

vinicius.ferreiraborges@outlook.com | +55 31 99594-5739 | Remote (GMT-3) | LinkedIn | GitHub

Portfolio Showcase | Medium

PROFILE

3+ years of experience, working with MS PowerBI, Python, SAS and SQL. I have built an complete data product of field operator services and build a web application with cloud connectors to provides a complete data governance for CEMIG, the most notable brazilian electric energy company globally.

As a **Data Analyst** able to create AAA products with a high market impact, I've led data teams, leveraging my strong background in data environments and engineering. I have also worked with LatAm clients in last years.

SKILLS

Languages:

Python, Java, SQL.

Softwares:

MS PowerBI, SAS, Metabase, SSIS, Pentaho, Git, GitHub, PowerBI Reporting Services, Figma.

Libraries & Frameworks:

Plotly.js, Streamlit, Seaborn, Pandas, Matplotlib, PPrint, SQLite3, SQLAlchemy, Scikit-Learn.

Databases & Cloud:

SQL Server, mySQL, PostgreSQL, SAP (CCS, R3, BW), MS Sharepoint, GCP.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Co-Data Leader, CEMIG S.A. [Number One PPP electric energy company by market cap in Brazil].

10/2023 – present Belo Horizonte, Brazil

- Enhanced a data project, establishing a fully automated, cloud-hosted system for customer feedback monitoring. Leveraged **SAS** for data flow and information delivery, optimizing the use of MS Sharepoint's shared environment, streamlining internal control, ready for managerial use.
- Devised an algorithm to assess service effectiveness, boosting accuracy by 84%. This led to the creation of a ranking system, now a staple in all CEMIG operational guidelines.
- Remastered **29 data projects**, and proposed restructuring to ensure stability and accountability in the sector's data.
- Achieved 82% accuracy in forecasting material costs and implemented visualization techniques increasing collections by over US\$992 million annually in CEMIG's disconnection services.

BI Software Engineer, CEMIG S.A.

10/2022 – 10/2023 Belo Horizonte, Brazil

- Engaged **+1,028 internal visitors in a workforce of 4,969** using Sharepoint cloud for self-service data access. Led Minas Gerais collaborators with visual marketing, scrum, and data-driven strategies.
- Streamlined data loading and viewing time **from 30 seconds to 1s**, ensuring **24/7** dashboard availability in leadership rooms, consolidating diverse indicators into a unified management board for simplified visualization of critical metrics.
- Constructed benchmarking panels to gauge CEMIG's competitiveness in the market. Worked with OKRs and KPIs, optimizing energy market indicators. This led to global leadership in supplier management and recognition from the Dow Jones Sustainability Index (DJSI World).

SOFTWARE SKILLS PROJECTS

Red Bull on-Premise Sales *⊗* Official Red Bull job simulation;

- Utilization of MS PowerBI to build the analysis;
- Developed UX/UI using Figma for an intuitive user experience;
- Implemented an Artificial Neural Network for sales forecasting using Plotly.js;
- Utilized the ETS native algorithm for enhanced forecasting accuracy;
- Communicated key observations to Red Bull team members, identifying why certain clients outperformed others.
- Employed active listening and social proof techniques to address client objections, leading to a more prominent display of Red Bull in their establishments.

Regressive model for marketing \mathscr{D}

- Utilizing Scikit-Learn (train_test_split), Plotly, Cufflinks, NumPy, Chart Studio;
- Application of the most used ML model on the market;
- Data Preparation;
- Data Modeling;
- Evaluating the data model using the r^2 coefficient;
- Data predicts;

LANGUAGES

CS50

edX ⊘

English B2	Spanish B1	
Portuguese Native		
EDUCATION		
Computer Science Anhembi Morumbi University ⊘		2022 – present
Full Stack on Data Science DNC Group ⊘		2023 – 2024

2024